Finding Aid for Universal Hagar’s Spiritual Church records, 1925-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Universal Hagar’s Spiritual Church records 1925-2014, 1999-2012
Universal Hagar’s Spiritual Church.
1.3 linear foot
2012055 Ba 2
Universal Hagar’s Spiritual Church was founded by Father George W. Hurley in 1923 in order “to promote the study of the science, phenomena and philosophy of spiritual religion” and is based in Detroit. The record group includes some material from the early years of the church’s operation, but with the bulk of the records documenting church activities after the year 2000.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was a give of the organization (donor no. 10601 ) and came to the library in 2011-2014.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
Father George W. Hurley (February 17, 1884-June 23, 1943), the founder of the Universal Hagar's Spiritual Church Association, was raised as a Baptist by his mother, Tina Hurley. At the age of seven he began to preach and challenge the traditional Baptist doctrine. He was ordained at the age of 11. After high school he went to Tuskegee Institute and Phelps Bible Hall Training School to receive ministerial training from Dr. E. J. Penny.
In 1918-19 Reverend Hurley met Father Elias D. Smith, founder of the Triumph the Church and Kingdom of God in Christ. Hurley was moved by Father Smith and his teachings and consequently joined. After several years, he reached the level of Elder and the presiding Prince of Michigan, but became dissatisfied with the teachings of the Triumph Church. After this he briefly joined the International Spiritual Church, but again he was not completely content.
On September 23, 1923 he founded the Universal Hagar's Spiritual Association. Father Hurley was concerned with both racial and economic disparities. He created the Hagar's School of Mediumship and Psychology (1924) and the Knights of the All Seeing Eye (1934 with Prince Thomas Surbadger) as extensions to the church.
The Universal Hagar's Spiritual Church Association has a number of objectives, including but not limited to teaching "the deeper truths of God, to promote the study of the science, phenomena and philosophy of spiritual religion, and to develop the true spiritual life among its members so that all members...attain the highest state of spiritual experience in this life as true worshippers of God."
Prince Alfred Bailey of New York became the fourth President of Universal Hagar's Spiritual Association after Mother Hatchett's death in 1977. In 1980, Prince Bailey passed and Princess Georgia Latimer of Michigan, the fourth child of Father & Mother Hurley, became the President. Princess Ida Lee Childs of Ohio took the reins in 1994 after Princess Latimer's death. Princess Childs appointed Princess Shirley Aquart of New Jersey as Acting President in April 2005. Princess Aquart was later made President after the passing of Princess Childs in 2007.
In 2012, the UHSCA boasted over 30 temples and missions in 14 states--Michigan, Ohio, Illinois, Indiana, New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania, Connecticut, Wisconsin, Maryland, Virginia, South Carolina, Georgia, and Alabama -- and was headquartered at 555 South Oakwood Blvd., Detroit, Michigan 48217.
The record group is arranged in three series: Background, Church Activities, and Publications.
Subjects:
Universal Hagar's Spiritual Church.; Hurley, George W., 1884-1943.; African American churches.; African American Spiritual Churches.; African American mediums.; Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Background
  The Background series includes information related to the early years of the church and its administration.
  - "Black Orientalism" by Jacob Dorman (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1931-1939 (Box 1)
  - Dedication of the Supreme Headquarters 2010 (Box 1)
  - Deeds 1964-2010 (Box 1)
  - Incorporation 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - "Meet the Boards" (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets circa 1925 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - "The Trial and Resurrection of Father Hurley" (Box 1)
- Church Activities
  The Church Activities series includes documents related to regular church activities. There are programs for the church's yearly meeting, calendars that document regular church holidays and other activities, guides to yearly meditations, and programs that outline the Biblical teachings for each week.
  - Annual Convenings 1997-2011, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - "The Application of Creative Thinking" (Box 1)
  - Calendars 2000-2012 (Box 1)
  - Meditations 1999-2014 (Box 1)
  - Sunday School 1999-2014 (Box 1)
  - Youth Programs
    - Bible Topics for Beginners 1999-2012 (Box 1)
    - "Get With the Program Youth Magazine," 1999-2004 (Box 1)
    - Junior Sunday School Quarterly 1931 (Box 1)
    - Youth Camp Notes 2007 (Box 1)
- Publications
  The Publications series includes newsletters published by the church. The coverage for "Hagar's Spiritual Rising Sun" and "The Aquarian Age" is scattered, but the years 1994-2012 for "The Aquarian Age" are largely complete.
  - "The Aquarian Age," 1938-1940 (copies) (Box 1)
  - "The Aquarian Age," 1934-1941 (Box 1)
  - "The Aquarian Age," 1994-2002 (Box 1)
  - "The Aquarian Age," 2003-2014, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - "The Aquarian Age," 1966-1986 (Box 2)
    (scattered)
  - "Hagar's Spiritual Rising Sun," 1929-1930 (Box 2)
  - "Hagar's Spiritual Rising Sun," 1929-1930, copies (Box 2)
  - "Hagar's Spiritual Rising Sun," 1929, oversize copies (Box 2)
  - "The Prophetic Age," 1931 (Box 2)